Uthaipon "Tao" Tantipongpipat

Machine Learning Engineer / Al Researcher

Orlando, FL, US uthaipon@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/uthaipon/

SUMMARY

Machine learning researcher at Twitter in responsible AI / AI ethics. Has driven successful projects (resulting in 3+ billions press click-read) and led company-wide engineers in applying research based on company data. Track record (10+) of top-tier computer science (ML/AI/Statistics) publications. A PhD from Georgia Tech focused on ML theory, optimization, with 1st place award from the US government on differential privacy.

EXPERIENCE

Twitter, remote US - Machine Learning Researcher

Jun 2020 - PRESENT

- Led Twitter's image cropping algorithmic bias audit resulting in a published academic paper and \$1.5M press ad equivalency and 3B readership from 500 news articles in 49 countries. Led to another follow-up work by team members resulted in additional \$1.4M,
 2.7B reads, and 800 articles from 47 additional countries, and contributed to the decision to remove the algorithm in production
- Proposed a 13-18% precision-recall video classification model improvement with no additional cost to partnering team to fix offensive misclassifications on Tweet topic annotations, and discovered correlation bias with demographics despite a lack of private individual data
- Established a data-driven guideline for company-wide engineers to adopt a inequality metric in A/B statistical testing, as well as winning business approval with company leadership that finally led to shipping the metric
- Provided statistical analysis to customer teams to evaluate and quantify bias in ML models;
 redesigned common ML statistical significance tests required for bias measurement
- Mentored a junior researcher
- Published two papers in social computing conference and one in data science journal

Microsoft, Redmond WA - Research Intern

May 2019 - July 2019

- Implemented privacy guarantee on large-scale natural language processing models (RNNs and LSTMs) to protect against personal deidentification due to model usage
- Developed novel correlation clustering algorithm with corresponding privacy analysis
- Researched private submodular optimization and surveyed literature for private stochastic gradient descent for improving training deep learning models
- Published one paper in the machine learning conference NeurlPS

EDUCATION

Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta GA

PhD in Algorithms, Combinatorics, and Optimization (ACO)

Aug 2016 - May 2020

Minor in Computational Learning Theory. GPA 4.00/4.00

University of Richmond, Richmond VA

BS in Mathematics, Honors with Thesis (Algebraic Combinatorics)

Aug 2012 - May 2016

Minor in Computer Science. GPA 3.97/4.00

University of Oxford, Oxford UK

Study Abroad Program in Mathematics and Computer Science Oct 2014 - Jun 2015

AWARDS

Academic:

•	Impact Recognition Award, CSCW (the social computing conference)	2021
•	ACO Outstanding Student Award (best PhD student in the year at the graduation)	2020
•	Best Reviewers of NeurlPS (top-tier machine learning conference)	2019
•	Full-merit 4-year scholarship for tuition and living expense, University of Richmond 2012	- 2016

Competitions:

1st Prize Award and People's Choice Award (\$20,000 total), The Unlinkable Data Challenge, National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), US Department of Commerce 2018
 Finalist, Tech Challenge programming competition, Illinois Technology Association, IL 2016
 2nd Place, ICPC Mid-Atlantic USA Regional Contest, Christopher Newport University 2015
 Honorable Mention (top 2.5%), William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition 2015
 Bronze Medal and Honorable Mention, Asia-Pacific Mathematics Olympiad (APMO) 2010, 2011
 Gold and Bronze Medals, IWYMIC International Mathematics Competition 2008, 2009

PUBLICATIONS

I have 11 peer-reviewed published papers, mainly in top-tier CS venues (such as NeurIPS, COLT, SODA). Topics include machine learning, responsible ML (fairness in ML), differential privacy, fairness, algorithms/theory, statistics, and Human-Centered Interaction (HCI)/Social Computing. My website www.uthaipon.com or Google Scholar has full details.

SKILLS

Technical: Responsible Al, model audit / model governance, cross-functional communications,

differential privacy, statistics. Python, Java, C++, SQL (BigQuery), Pytorch, pandas,

numpy, scipy, Git, CVXOPT, MATLAB, Mathematica, LaTeX

Languages: Thai (native); English (full proficiency)